<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Christus Dei, the Lords annoynted. Or, A theologicall discourse, wherein is proved, that the regall or monarchicall power of our soveraigne lord King Charles is not of humane, but of divine right, and that God is the sole efficient cause thereof, and not the people. Also that every monarch is above the whole common-wealth, and is not onely major singulis, but major vniversis. Written in answer to a late printed pamphlet intituled, Observations upon some of His Majesties late answers and expresses.</title>
            <author>Jones, John, d. 1660.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 32 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 8 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A87633</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99869037</idno>
  <idno type="VID">121397</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240953475</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing J961A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E92_4</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R21022</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99869037</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99869037e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A87633)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 121397)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 16:E92[4])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Christus Dei, the Lords annoynted. Or, A theologicall discourse, wherein is proved, that the regall or monarchicall power of our soveraigne lord King Charles is not of humane, but of divine right, and that God is the sole efficient cause thereof, and not the people. Also that every monarch is above the whole common-wealth, and is not onely major singulis, but major vniversis. Written in answer to a late printed pamphlet intituled, Observations upon some of His Majesties late answers and expresses.</title>
                  <author>Jones, John, d. 1660.</author>
                  <author>Morton, Thomas, 1564-1659.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 13, [1] p., [1] leaf of plates : port.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by His Maiesties command at Oxford [i.e. London],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1643.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to John Jones (DNB). Also sometimes attributed to Thomas Morton (NUC).</note>
                  <note>"Observations" was by Henry Parker.</note>
                  <note>"A London counterfeit edition, published about March 6, 1642/3, as Thomason received it on March 7" -- Madan.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: The "3" crossed out in the imprint date; "March. 7".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="personal_name">Parker, Henry, 1604-1652. --  Observations upon some of His Majesties late answers and expresses --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Divine right of kings --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Theology, Doctrinal --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-11 </date>
            <label>John Latta </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-11 </date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="frontispiece">
            <pb facs="tcp:121397:1"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <head>CHARLES BY THE GRACE OF GOD Kinge of England, Scotland France and Ireland defendor of the faith, etc:</head>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:121397:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>CHRISTVS DEI,</hi> The LORDS Annoynted OR, A Theologicall Discourse, wherein is proved, that the Regallor Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chicall power of Our Soveraigne Lord KING CHARLES Is not of Humane, but of divine Right, and that GOD is the sole Efficient cause thereof, and not the people.</p>
            <p>Also that every MONARCH is above the whole Common-wealth, and is not onely <hi>Major Singulis,</hi> but <hi>Major Vniversis.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Written in <hi>Answer</hi> to a late <hi>Printed Pamphlet</hi> intitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, <hi>Observations upon some of His</hi> MAIESTIES <hi>late Answers</hi> and <hi>Expressess.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>1 Pe.t 2.13.</bibl>
               <p>
                  <hi>Subjecti estote omni humanae creaturae propter Dominum, sive Regi quasi Praecellenti.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Submit your selves to every Ordinance of man, for the Lord's sake, whether it be to the King as supreme.</p>
            </q>
            <p>Printed by His MAIESTIES Command AT OXFORD. 1643.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="discourse">
            <pb facs="tcp:121397:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:121397:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>CHRISTVS DEI,</hi> OR, A Theologicall Discourse, wherein is proved, that Regall Power is not of Humane, but of Divine Right, and that God only is the Efficient cause thereof, and not the People.</head>
            <div type="preface">
               <head>Preface.</head>
               <p n="1">1 <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here is a Book come forth of late, barely intituled, Observations upon some of His Majesties late An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swers and Expresses, without any name of the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor or place where it was printed. Wherein the Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>server (so I must call him not knowing him by any other name) aimes chiefly and directly to prove, that the Heredita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, Regall, and Monarchicall power of our now present dread So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraigne King <hi>Charles,</hi> is inferiour and subject to the power of the now present Parliament.</p>
               <p n="2">2 Which to evince he undertakes to lay down the originall foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of all Regall power whatsoever, according to the efficient &amp; finall causes thereof. And having made the finall cause to be the sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fety of the people, together with their Civill or Politicall happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse; he also makes the efficient cause to be, not God, but only the
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:121397:3"/>people, and the instrumentall cause of conveying and deriving this Regall Power to be, not any divine law, nor nothing else (amongst Christians) but the meere humane pactions and Agreements of the Politick body of the people. And then arguing by a rule in nature; that <hi>quicquid efficit tale est magis tale,</hi> he issueth out this just infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence (as he calleth it) that though the King be <hi>singulis major,</hi> yet he is <hi>universis minor,</hi> and therefore inferior and subject in power to the Parliament.</p>
               <p n="3">3 Having perused this discourse, and finding it to be most inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious to Regall Power or Monarchy, contrary to the true princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of State and Divinity, or Orthodox Christian Doctrine: I thought I might do my King and Country good service, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fute these desperate and more than dangerous Positions, by decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring and proving the true Originall foundation, according to the fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall and efficient causes of Regall or Monarchicall Power: which (with Gods good helpe) I hope to do perspicuosly in the few en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suing Paragraphes.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="1" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. 1.</hi> Of the Primary Finall cause; as also of the efficient cause of all Civill Societies or Republiques.</head>
               <p>Because whatsoever is done, is done for some end or purpose, without which it should not have been done, nor had a being: ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is the constant Doctrine of all Philosophers, that the end is the chief and Principall of all causes: and therefore, for methods sake I will begin with it. Now to find out the Primary end of all Civill Societies or Commonwealths, we, that are Christians, must reflect attentively upon those words of the holy Ghost. Pro. 16.4. <hi>Universa propter semet ipsum operatus est Dominus.</hi> By which we are ascertained, that God Almighty created not only all other Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures; but all man-kind also, as for their Primary end, for himselfe, and his own Praise and glory.</p>
               <p>And as for man in particular, God created him to his owne i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage and likeness, endowing him with an understanding and a wil, that he might know how to honour and love his Creator, and by such love &amp; honour might finally become happy in the fruition of
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:121397:3"/>his eternall, unspeakable and inestimable glory in heaven: for means whereto, first God dictated certaine Divine precepts and prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples unto man, &amp; imprinted them with his very creation upon his natural reason (for which cause they are called divine naturall Laws written in every mans heart, saith St. <hi>Paul. Rom.</hi> 2.15.) that every man might be equally capeable to know them, and equally obliged to obey them. Secondly, God infused into him <hi>Faith, hope,</hi> and <hi>Charity,</hi> and other supernaturall virtues, all tending to this conduce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that man following them as his guides, might, through his obedience to God, attain to his owne salvation. Thirdly, to binde man more strongly to his subjection, and to make it appeare more illustriously unto him, that therein principally consisted his Wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare, as the very End and Center, for and to which he was created, He gave him an expresse divine Law, not to eate of the tree in the midst of Paradise upon pain of death. Fourthly, by Revelation he instructed him in many particular sacred formes and Rites of exte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour divine worship, as sacrifice and others; for though we read not any where in holy Writ, that <hi>Adam</hi> offered Sacrifice, no more than we doe of <hi>Isaac;</hi> yet we read there that <hi>Cain</hi> and <hi>Abel</hi> did, <gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd that <hi>Abraham</hi> and <hi>Iacob</hi> did. But it cannot be imagined that <hi>Cain</hi> add <hi>Abel</hi> were the first Inventors of this most, religious and divine worship, (no more than that <hi>Isaac</hi> did neglect it) but by Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall tradition and examdle they received it from <hi>Adam.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. All which duely considered, it will appeare evidently, that the primary end for which all men are created, is to serve, honour, love, obey, and worship God. From whence it followes, that this being mans highest and principallest concerne, it ought al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so to be his highest and pincipallest care to attend to it. But most certaine it is, that men, living diided and scattered over the face of the world without the instruction and assistance one of another cannot possibly performe this for every particular mans behoofe, as is requisite. And therefore from this finall cause arose primarily a necessity amongst men to unite and combine themselves into ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill Societies and Common-wealths. This end could not be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fixed by men; but men were created for this end by God. And therefore this is the primary, spirituall, supernaturall, and divine fi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nall cause of all Republikes, to which every other end must be b<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> secondary, subordinate, and subservient.</p>
               <p n="4">
                  <pb n="4" facs="tcp:121397:4"/> 4 And from hence it followeth further, that since on the one side no naturall agent can by it's naturall power compasse the attain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of a supernaturall end; and on the other side Civill Societies ought not to be instituted in vaine: we must needs conclude, that the Primary efficient cause of all Common-wealths is only God.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>PARAGR. 2.</hi> Of the Secondary finall Cause, and also the only Efficient Cause of all Civill Societies and Republiques.</head>
               <p n="1">1 Every Creature in the world strives to preserve its own kind. We see what paines and Care Beasts and Birds take to reare their younglings. Trees and Plants beare fruits and seeds to produce the like when they are perished. Yea, the inanimate Creatures (accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to their predominant Element and mixture) strive every one to obtaine and enjoy their Center. And all this not only for their own particular, but also for the harmonious Accommodation and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>servation of the Vniverse, the great and most excellent work of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, wherein she doth nothing in vaine. But in vaine had man been, if he also had not been provided of necessary meanes towards the Preservation of his kind. For which cause God said it was not good for man to be alone: and therefore gave him a Woman to be his Helper, that so by meanes of generation he might propagate his of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spring to the worlds end.</p>
               <p n="2">2 This Preservation then of mankind, is the maine naturall and secondary end of man. And to this end God gave him his blessing to increase and multiply, from whence ariseth, that of necessity there must be at least private families. But man and Woman finding (by wofull experience) most true what God said to <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eve;</hi> that he should eate his bread in the sweat of his browes, that she should bring forth her children in paine, found also presently, that every private family is not sufficient of it self to maintaine this work of Preservation, without the help of one another. For first, to say no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of womens deliveries in child-birth, which cannot possibly alwayes and every where be performed requisitely by themselves and their families, without the help of some other, or others: and
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:121397:4"/>yet even upon this the Preservation of mankind holds a most neces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sary and principall dependance. I will only speak of mans part, who with the sweat of his browes, with extreame toile and labour must provide food and cloathing, and all other necessary supports and sustentations for his family. But to do this, he must of necessity (I speak not of barbarous inhumane people) have some certaine place of aboad; and in this he must have some peculiar right, some propriety of possession, by vertue whereof he may reape the fruits of the earth, and maintaine his Cattel. And how shall every private family be able to do this with Securitie? will not every one strive for the best possession? will not the shepheards of <hi>Abraham</hi> and <hi>Lot,</hi> and of <hi>Isaac</hi> and <hi>Gerara</hi> fall to contention for water and pastures, and such like other necessary elbow roome? And in these uncivill and unsociable quarrels, must not all private families be made like to the fishes of the Sea. <hi>Hab.</hi> 11, 13, 14. where the stronger must devoure the weaker?</p>
               <p n="3">3 Secondly God endowed man in his creation with an under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing and a will. This understanding is of that infinite capacity, that it hath for it's Adaequate Object <hi>omne ens</hi> as it is <hi>verum.</hi> And man therefore is in perpetuall and restlesse search of knowledge, to perfect his understanding by experience and learning. The will also hath for her adaequate Object <hi>omne ens</hi> as it is <hi>bonum.</hi> And man therefore is in perpetuall pursuite of Reciprocall love to perfect his will by friendship and Iustice. Over and above these, God gave to man the faculty of speech, to be the Reciprocall conveyance of learning and friendship. So as for this very reason <hi>Aristotle</hi> said ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellently well, that man is by nature a sociable Creature, for neither learning, nor friendship, nor justice (in which consists essentially mans Civill or Politicall happinesse) nor safety or security (which is the only preservative of mans very being) can possibly be acquired and maintained in the division of men in their private families. And therefore for this very end it was naturally necessary for men to u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite and associate themselves into Civill Societies and Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, that so they might preserve their Kind.</p>
               <p>From the learning, Experience, and Industry of the understand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing proceed all Arts, Tillage, Manufactures, Trade, and Traffique,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:121397:5"/>which bring in Gaine, and that brings plenty, from the friendship and justice of the will proceed Peace and security: in which secure peace and plenty consisteth perfect <hi>salus populi.</hi> Now since this this cannot be had in divided private families, &amp; without this there can be no preservation of Man-kind, it followes; that Civill Socie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties or Commonwealths are naturally necessary. Whose naturall finall cause is truely and onely (in the manner as I have explicated) <hi>Salus populi.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now furthermore, seeing that Common-wealth is not the designe of Art and Invention of particular men, nor of any positive law of theirs, but proceeds from the Common necessity of all man-kind, intimated unto them by the Law of nature, of which God is the sole cause and Author: it followeth that the efficient cause of all Republiques is onely God.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. 3.</hi> Of the Finall and Efficient cause of Civill Power in a Commonwealth.</head>
               <p n="1">1. As for the finall cause there is little or no difficulty; for seeing that the finall cause of every thing must needs be that, which that thing necessarily refers unto, as to its end for which it is done or hath its being: it is manifest, that since civill societies have for their naturall and secondary finall cause <hi>Salus populi;</hi> the power also which must not be <hi>ad destructionem,</hi> but <hi>ad aedificationem,</hi> to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine those civill societies, can have no other finall cause, but that whereunto they direct and are directed, which is <hi>Salus Populi.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. The materiall cause in which this power originall, resides and inheres; as the former to make up a compleat Body of a Common-wealth, is the people. And so the Observer sayth ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie well in this kind of cause, power is originally inherent in the people: most certaine then it is, that even at the very first uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting themselves into a Civill society, there is an inherent power in the people to governe themselves, and by such Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to preserve themselves in safety. For this is the onely necessary naturall end for which they met (as I have very briefely shewene before) that they might bee able and
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:121397:5"/>powerfull to secure themselves, and preserve their kind. But this meeting would have beene in vain, and this preservation wholly made frustrate, if there were not this power inherent in them.</p>
               <p n="3">3. If in the naturall body of man there were not an interiour Directive Governing Power to guide every particular member in the operative use of its function, and to contrive those operations to the mutuall good of one another, and the conservation of the whole man; that body could not possibly but suddenly perish. For if the teeth will not chew, nor the throat swallow, nor the hands reach, nor the feet stirre, nor the eyes look out, when nature re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires her necessary food, she and they and all must starve. So in a politicall Body; if all members should do what they list, and should not be compelled by some absolute power to contribute their strengths and endevours to the preservation of one another, and the whole Community, it would be but <hi>Regnum in se divisum,</hi> that of necessity must fall to desolation, as the holy Ghost confirms also else where, saying <hi>Prov.</hi> 11.14 <hi>Ubi non est Gubernator dssipa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitur Populus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4 The maine difficulty is: who is the efficient cause of this power, Wherein, not to be tedious to my Reader, but to yield him the satisfaction of his expectation in a briefe and resolute answer, I present unto him this Decretory Assertion. This power is not a humane but a divine Right; and God onely is the immediate effi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient cause thereof. This I prove by five Arguments.</p>
               <p n="5">5. <hi>Arg.</hi> 1. There is a rule in nature (to use the Observers owne words) <hi>Quoddat esse dat consequentia ad esse.</hi> But the <hi>esse</hi> of a Republike cannot have a <hi>simpliciter esse</hi> without the <hi>esse</hi> of this power. Therefore he that is the efficient cause of the Repub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique, is also the efficient cause of this power. But (as I have prov'd before SECT. 2. <hi>n.</hi> 5.) God is the sole efficient cause of all Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>publiques, therfore he is also the sole efficient cause of this power.</p>
               <p n="6">6 <hi>Arg.</hi> 2. The Primary finall cause of Civill Societies (as I have prov'd SECT. 1.) is divine worship, which man could not prefix to himselfe as his end, but he was created by God for and to that end, and onely God prefixed that end to man. Therefore this is a divine end which cannot be atchieved without a divine
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:121397:6"/>Power (as I have also proved in the same <hi>Section, n.</hi> 4.) onely God then is the immediate Efficient cause of this power.</p>
               <p n="7">7. And from thence it proceeds, that Kings, acknowledging themselves to have received this divine power, principally for this primary end, their Oathes at their Coronation are (as the Obser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver very grutchingly granteth) more precise in the care of Cano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicall Priviledges, and of Bishops and Clergy men, than of the Commonalty: and not from the reason which he gives. <hi>viz.</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause they were penned by Popish Bishops. For whether the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shops were Popish or Protestant, surely they are not to be blamed <hi>ex hoc capite,</hi> but most highly to be reverenced, that according to their profession and duty they put Kings in mind, in the first place, of divine worship, and their owne and their peoples eternall salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion depending thereupon. And I cannot understand why the Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>server should give that reason, but onely to seduce the Vulgar into a base and profane misconceiving and vilifying of the royal pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of Kings, and their sacred Oathes. For Popish without all doubt in his Dictionary signifieth superstitious at least, if not Idolatrous. But, if it be superstition for a man to be more precise in the care of Divine Worship, and his soules everlasting salvation, than of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other his temporall end or affaire (see <hi>Section</hi> 1. <hi>n.</hi> 3.) in vaine then have all Christians hitherto believed that they were in a true Religion. Let the Observer consider what censure he deserves for thus finding fault with Kings Oathes, and whether hee gives not just cause of suspicion, that he is rather an Atheist than a Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an. It is well knowne to all Christians, that <hi>Quaerite primùm Reg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num Dei &amp; justitiam ejus</hi> is no invention of Popish Bishops, but our Blessel Saviours owne Doctrine and Rule, not only to Bishops, but to all Kings and people whatsoever, as the principall, to which as an <hi>Accessorium</hi> followes, <hi>&amp; haec omnia adjicientur vobis. Mat.</hi> 6.33.</p>
               <p n="8">8. <hi>Arg.</hi> 3 When private families first joyned themselves in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a Common body of society, before any <hi>Condictum,</hi> Paction, or Agreement amongst themselves, to enact positive Lawes for their government, there was an inherent power in them to enact such Lawes. For who can make a Law without a power? But this power, not being the effect, but the most necessary cause of
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:121397:6"/>all humane pactions, or positive Lawes, cannot have its origen from man, but onely from God. <hi>Ergo</hi> God is the sole Efficient cause of this power.</p>
               <p n="9">9. <hi>Arg.</hi> 4. When men first associated themselves into a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth, they were all of equall Right and Power, so that none (I speake of severall families still as before) could challenge su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periority the one over the other. For, this divine naturall power, <hi>viz. Se defendere, &amp; vim vi repellere,</hi> was inherent in every one of them, and obligeing them. The power then which accrewed to to the aggregation of the whole society, was not made but brought, as being no other than what was in all and every particular Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of that society before. But that is a Divine power, and the immediate effect of God. <hi>Ergo.</hi> And indeed in the due mnnaging or excercising of this divine naturall law of <hi>se defendendo,</hi> and <hi>vim vi repellendo</hi> consists totally the security and <hi>Salus Populi,</hi> and the power of the Common-wealth to maintain it.</p>
               <p n="10">10. <hi>Arg.</hi> 5. God Almighty is so solely the Legislator and Author of his owne Lawes, without the concurrence or consent of any other Councell, (<hi>quis enim consiliarius ejus fuit, aut quis pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>or dedit ei? Rom,</hi> 11.33.) That they have their establishment onely in and by his own will. So that no power whatsoever of his Creatures, can by any contraition against him, invalid or annull those Lawes. But <hi>non occides</hi> is a Divine naturall Law and precept expressed in the Decalogue. Therefore no Pactions or agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of men can give this power of putting a man to death, no more than <hi>Cain</hi> could kill <hi>Abel.</hi> But on the other side it is ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifest, that Republikes have a lawfull power of putting men to death, without which they could not preserve their owne safety. Therefore they have it from God. And how soon God gave this power to men I know not, nor cannot find, untill after the floud; when <hi>Gen.</hi> 9.6. we read this expresse positive divine Law and precept given to the Civill Magistrate. <hi>Quicunque effuderit hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manum sanguinem, fundetur sanguis illius.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="section">
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:121397:7"/>
               <head>SECT. 4.</head>
               <p n="1">1. The Finall Cause of Regall power must of necessity be the same that is of the Common-wealth, because the King is the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ministrator of the power of the Common-wealth, to the same end no doubt, for which it was first ordained: of which having spoken largely before, I have no need to say any thing here.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The maine question is, who is the efficient cause of Regall or Monarchicall power? Which the Observer boldly averres to be, not God, but the people. And upon this false ground he vents all those swarmes of false inferences throughout his whole discourse.</p>
               <p n="3">3. But before I lay down the true Resolution or this question, I must desire my reader to mark with good heed the great difference that is between the power it selfe of a Common-wealth, and the authority to administer that power: for the people may be the Ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient Cause of this second, though not of the first. As for ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, the Aldermen of London may elect, nominate, and consti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute such or such a man to be their Lord Major to administer the power that belongs to the Corporation of that City; and herein they may be the Efficient cause of his Authority to administer the power of the City, but not of his power; because that is the gift of the King by his Charter, of which his Majesty therefore is the onely efficient cause, and not the Aldermen, nor all the people of that Corporation whatsoever.</p>
               <p n="4">4. I have proved all along in the precedent <hi>Sections,</hi> that the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill power of a Common-wealth, is not a humane, but divine pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, of which, not the people, but God onely is the Efficient cause. It is true indeed, that it is in the voluntary election of the people to authorize one, or few, or more with the administration of this power. And as long as this Authority is still elective in the people, they may by consent of the major part alter their forme of Guber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation into Democraticall Oligarchicall, Aristocraticall, or Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchicall, as they please. And herein the Observer saith truely, that God is no more the Author of Regall, than of Aristocraticall power: for whether this power be in many, or in one, it is still the
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:121397:7"/>same divine power of the Common-wealth, though diversly ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ministred, of which God onely is the efficient cause. But when the people have once resigned up all their authority into the hands of one, and his heires for ever, so that now it is not any longer ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive in them, but hereditary in him: then not onely the power, but the authority also to administer that power is solely inherent in him and his heires, unalterably and irrevocably for ever.</p>
               <p n="5">5. This then is my first Assertion. The Efficient cause of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gall or Monarchicall power, is not the people, but onely God. I speak in this Assertion, not of conditionall Princes, but onely of absolute Kings and Monarchs. My first proofe then is. When the people create a King, they elect his person, and authorize him with the administration of the absolute power which is inherent in the whole Common-wealth to governe it selfe: otherwise he is no absolute King, of whom onely I speak, and so doth the observer also. But this power (as I have proved) is not an humane, but a divine power, of which God onely is the Efficient Cause. Therefore God onely, and not the people is the Efficient Cause of Regall power.</p>
               <p n="6">6. My second proofe, God saith expressely, <hi>Prov.</hi> 8.15. <hi>Per me Reges regnant, &amp;c.</hi> Then their Dominion or power by which they reigne is immediately from God. Christ saith to <hi>Pilate, Joh.</hi> 19.11. <hi>Non haberes potestatem, &amp;c. nisi tibi datum esset desuper.</hi> Then this power is not from below from men; but from above, from God. St. <hi>Paul</hi> saith, <hi>Rom,</hi> 13.1. <hi>Omnis anima potestatibus sublimionibus subd. ta sit: non est enim potestas nisi à Deo.</hi> And <hi>qui resistit Potestati, Dei Ordinationi resistit.</hi> And, <hi>non sine causa gladium portat.</hi> For what cause? <hi>Dei enim minister est, vindex in iram, &amp;c.</hi> Then Regall Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer is Divine power and the Ordinance of God, wherein the King is not the peoples, but Gods Ministers, as being invested and annoynted interiorly in his person by him with a Divine power; of which the exteriour Vnction is a sacred, Ceremonous, Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monefactive and solemne Testimony. And for this cause <hi>Gyrus</hi> though a Heathen King is called by God himselfe. <hi>Isay</hi> 45.1. <hi>Christus meus,</hi> Gods own annoynted. The holy King <hi>Josaphat</hi> saith to those whom he had constituted <hi>Judge.</hi> 2. <hi>Paralip.</hi> 19.6. <hi>Non
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:121397:8"/>hominis exercetis judicium, sed Domini.</hi> Then it is not a humane pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, but a divine power by which the King doth judge and rule his people.</p>
               <p>From hence I infer two Corollaries.</p>
               <p n="7">7. The first: That there is a two-fold trust in the King. The one of his power. The other of the administration of his power. The first is Gods trust unto him, to exercise his divine judgements. The second, is the peoples, to administer it <hi>Propter salutem populi.</hi> But if he swerve herein; seeing that the power is divine and residing and inhering onely in him, and not in the people, he is not liable to the people, but onely to God.</p>
               <p n="8">8. The second Corollarie. As God is the sole efficient cause of Regall power; so the instrumentall cause which conveighes this power, is the divine naturall Law obliging men to unite themselves into Civil societies. For God gives a power to men to govern them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves by obliging them to unite themselves. And consequently the election of the people (with all the Observers pactions and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greements) is but <hi>Causa sine qua non,</hi> by way of approximation, that this divine power may reside in those few, or more, or one rather than in any other. As in my former example <hi>n.</hi> 3. The efficient cause of the Lord Majors power is onely the King. The instru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental cause by which this power is derived unto him, is the Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of the City, granted to them at pleasure, more strictly or more largely by the King. And the Aldermens election of this or that particular man, is but the approximation, that the Kings power may reside in him to governe the City, rather than in any other.</p>
               <p n="9">9, My second Assertion. Every absolute King (invested and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nointed with a divine power by God himself to exercise his judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments through the election of the people to be sole administrator therof) is in power <hi>super totam Rempublicam;</hi> Superiour absolutely over the whole Common-wealth. And therefore is not only <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jor singulis,</hi> but <hi>Major Vniversis,</hi> and <hi>super omnes simul.</hi> This Asser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is evident out of the former. For the power that was inherent in the whole Common-wealth to exercise Gods judgements, and to governe and preserve it selfe, was a divine power, not only <hi>super singulos,</hi> but <hi>super omnes simul,</hi> and therefore <hi>Major Universis.</hi> But this
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:121397:8"/>power is now totally and absolutely inherent in the King only. <hi>Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go</hi> he is <hi>super totam Rempublicam:</hi> and <hi>Major Universis.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="10">10. In confirmation of this argument, I argue thus. Either the whole power of the Common-wealth is in one, or no. If no, then he is no absolute King or Monarch, contrary to our supposition. But if he be a Monarch, I aske againe; if there be a powet in the Common-wealth, which is not in him, is it subordinate to his pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, or no? if it be subordinate, then his power is above that pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, and so <hi>super totam Rempublicam,</hi> and <hi>Major Universis.</hi> If it be not, then there are <hi>simul &amp; semel</hi> two supream Civill powers in a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth, two supream contrary Masters at once to be obeyed, one and the same individuall Kingdom and Gubernation, and yet divided against it selfe, which are most absurd and impossible.</p>
               <p n="11">11. From hence it is evident, that his Majesty sayd most truely, and most learnedly; that the administration of the whole power of the Common-wealth being committed in trust absolutely and irrevocably to him and his heires for ever, it is impossible that a power above that trust should be committed to others.</p>
               <p n="12">12. This the Observer in effect plainly confesseth. But relapsing in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his wonted Paroxismes of strong malice against Regall Power, he labours (by his most false erroneous Principle <hi>Rex est minor U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niversis</hi>) and tire himselfe in vaine to answer it. And because the strength of all his long tedious and farraginous discourse depends wholly upon these two false grounds, <hi>viz.</hi> that the people is the efficient cause of Regall power; And that <hi>Rex est minor Universis;</hi> and I have manifestly confuted them both: I presume I have also sufficiently confuted all the rest; and therefore conclude in those sacred words, <hi>Data est a Domino Potestas Regibus, &amp; virtus ab Altis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>simo.</hi> Power is given to Kings of the Lord, and Soveraignty from the highest. <hi>Sapient.</hi> 6.3.</p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>